现在我们理解了什么是分组密码
So now that we understand what block
ciphers are, let's look at a classic
我们看一个经典的例子叫数据加密标准
DES。简单提醒一下大家
example called the Data Encryption
Standard. So, just a quick reminder. Block
分组密码将N位输入映射到N位输出
ciphers basically map N bits of input to N
bits of output. And we talked about two
我们讨论了两个经典的例子，3DES和AES。
本节我们讲DES
canonical examples, triple DES and AES. In
this segment, we're gonna talk about DES,
然后在下一节讨论3DES
and we'll talk about triple DES, actually,
in the next segment. And then I also
我之前提过，分组密码由迭代构造。特别地
mentioned before that block ciphers are
often built by iteration. In particular,
我们看的分组密码里的迭代
we're gonna look at block ciphers that are
built by a form of iteration where a key K
开始时密钥K被扩张成一组回合密钥，
然后回合函数应用到输入信息上
is first expanded into a bunch of round
keys. And then a round function is applied
一次又一次，所有轮次
to the input message, again and again and
again. And essentially, after all these
都完事后，我们获得最终的密文，对吧？
round functions are applied, we obtain the
resulting cipher text, okay? And again,
我们要看看数据加密标准DES如何工作
what we're gonna look at, how DES, the
data encryption standard, uses this
使用这个格式。我想更清楚点
事实上，指定一个这种类型的分组密码
format. I just wanna be clear that, in
fact, to specify a block cipher of this
需要指定密钥扩张的机制
type, one needs to specify the key
expansion mechanism, and one needs to
需要指定回合函数。本节我关注回合函数
specify the round function. In the segment
here, I'm gonna focus on the round
我不会讨论太多密钥扩张的细节
function, and I'm not gonna talk much
about key expansion. But I just wanted to
但我想提一下，事实上，密钥扩张也是描述
分组密码的重要部分
mention that, in fact, key expansion is
also a big part of describing how block
好，那么我们来看看DES的历史
cipher works. Okay, so let's talk about
the history of DES. Essentially, in the
1970年代初，IBM发现他们的消费者要求
early 1970s, IBM realized that their
customers are demanding some form of
某种形式的加密。于是它们成立了一个
密码小组，组长是Horst Feistel
encryption. And so they formed a crypto
group, and the head of that group, was
在70年代初，他设计了Lucifer密码
Horst Feistel, who, in the early 70s,
designed a cipher called Lucifer. Now,
有趣的是，事实上Lucifer有很多变种
it's interesting. In fact Lucifer had a
number of variations but one of the later
但是其中一种新变种有128位的密钥长度
variations in fact had a key length that
was 128 bits and a block length that's
分组大小也是128位。好，1973年
政府发现它买了很多商业的
also 128 bits. Okay, in 1973 the governor
realized that it's buying many commercial
已下架的计算机，所有它希望这些计算机
提供商能有个好的算法
off-the-shelf computers and so it wanted
its suppliers to actually have a good grip
可以在卖给政府的产品中有用
to algorithm that they could use in
products sold to the government. So in
1973年国家安全局（当时的称谓）
1973 the National Bureau of Standards as
it was called at the time put out a
放出了一个征求分组密码的项目
选中的会成为联邦标准
request for proposals for a block cipher
that is going to become a federal
事实上IBM提交了Lucifer的一个变种
standard. And in fact IBM submitted a
variant of Lucifer. That variant actually
这个变种经过一些标准化的修改之后
went through some modification during the
standardization process and then finally
最后于1976年由国家安全局采用为联邦标准
in 1976, the national bureau standard
adopted DES as a federal standard. And, in
事实上DES很有意思，它的密钥长度比Lucifer要少
fact, for DES it's interesting that the
key length was far reduced from Lucifer.
仅为56位，分组大小也减少到64位
It's only 56 bits. And the block length
was also reduced to 64 bits. And in
事实上这些决定，特别是减少密钥长度
fact, these decisions, especially the
decision to reduce the key length, is
是导致很多人怀疑DES寿命的原因
going to be a key length yield of DES and
was a source of many complaints over its
特别地，早在1997年，DES就被穷举密钥攻击
life. In particular, already back in 1997,
DES was broken by exhaustive search
破解了，意思是让计算机遍历所有
2的56次方个可能的密钥
meaning that a machine was able to search
through all two to the 56 possible keys to
来找到特定的密钥。事实上我们会
recover a particular challenge key. And in
fact we're going to talk about exhaustive
详细讨论一下穷举攻击。这个问题很有趣
search quite a bit. It's quite an
interesting question, and there are
有很多方法可以来抵抗穷举攻击
various ways to defend against exhaustive
search. And basically this 1997 experiment
1997年的实验预示了DES的末路，
它意味着DES本身不再安全了
kinda spelled the doom of DES. It meant
that DES is itself, is no longer secure.
于是国家标准研究所对外发出请求
And as a result, the National Institute of
Standards, as it became known, issued a
征求下一代分组密码方案
request for proposals. For our next
generation's block cipher standard and in
在2000年，它在Rijndael的基础上研发标准
2000 it standardized on a cipher called Rijndael.
Which became the advanced encryption
成为了高级加密标准AES。我们稍后讨论AES
standard, AES. And we'll talk about AES
later on. But in this segment, I wanna
本节我想描述DES的工作原理
DES是个(历史上)异常成功的密码
describe how DES works. Now, DES is a
cipher, it's an amazingly successful
它被用于银行业界。事实上
cipher. It's been used in the banking
industry. In fact, there's a classic
有一个经典的网络叫做电子打扫房间
network called the Electronic
Clearing House, which banks use to clear
银行使用这个网络来处理支票
DES被用来保护这些事务的完整性
checks with one another. And DES is used
for integrity in those transactions. It's
DES也被商用。事实上它不久前很流行
also used in commerce. In fact, it was
very popular up until recently, as the
曾是网络的主要加密机制
当然，现在它已被AES和其他密码替代
main encryption mechanism for the web. Of
course, now, that's been replaced with AES
总的来说，从应用的角度来看
DES是个非常成功的密码
and other ciphers. Overall, it's a
very successful cipher in terms of
DES也有非常丰富的被攻击历史
deployment. DES also has a very rich
history of attacks, which we'll talk about
我们将在下一节中讨论DES的攻击
现在，我们讨论DES的构造
in the next segment. Okay, so now, let's
talking about the construction of DES. So,
DES背后的核心思想叫做Feistel网络
由Horst Feistel提出
the core idea behind DES is what's called
a Feistel network, due to Horst Feistel.
这是一个非常聪明的方法，
来根据任意函数F1到FD构造分组密码
And basically, it's a very clever idea for
building the block cipher out of arbitrary
好的，那么我们有这些函数F1到FD
functions, F1 to FD. Okay so imagine we
have these functions F1 to FD
它们从n位字符串映射到n位字符串
现在这些是任意的函数
that happens to match n bits to n bits.
Now these are arbitrary functions,
它们不一定是可逆的，而我们要做的
they don't have to be invertible or
anything. What we want to do is build an
是根据这D个函数构造出一个可逆函数。
我们实现的方法是
invertible function out of those D
functions and the way we'll do it is by
构造一个新的函数，我们记为F
将2n位字符串映射到2n位字符串
building a new function we'll call capital
F that maps 2n bits to 2n bits.
构造方法写在这里了
那么这里有我们的输入
And the construction is described right
here. So here we have our inputs. You
大家注意，有两个n位的分组
换句话说，输入实际上是2n位
notice, there are two blocks of n bits.
In other words, the input is actually
R和L分布代表右和左。典型地
2n bits. The R and L stand for right and
left. Typically, people describe a
我们从高层到底层来表述Feistel网络。
这里n位字符串分左右
Feistel network from top to bottom. In
which case, these n bits really would be
但这里我横向描述会更方便些
right and left. But here it is more
convenient for me to describe it
如果我们跟着右边R走
horizontally. So if we follow the R
inputs. You realize it basically gets
发现它被左边输出原样复制了一份
没有发生任何改变，对吧？
copied into the L output, without any
change at all. Okay? However, the L
但是输入L有些变化。将输入R
inputs, is changed somewhat. What happens
is, basically, the R inputs is fit into
应用函数F1，然后结果和L0异或，就成为了新的R1
the function F1 and the result is then
XORed with L0 and that becomes the new R1
(编号表示第几回合的结果)
好，那么这个叫做Feistel网络的一个回合
input. Okay, so this is called one round
of a Feistel network, and is done using
它是使用函数F1的。现在我们再做一遍，使用函数F2来完成
the function F1. Now we do this again with
another round of the Feistel network
Feistel网络，然后我们一次又一次地做
with the function F2, and we do it again
and again and again, 'till we get to the
直到最后一轮，用函数FD完成之。
最终所得的结果
last round, and we do it again with the
function FD. And finally, the output is
记为Rd和Ld。那么如果你乐意，我们能
写成符号的形式，就是说
Rd, Ld. Okay. So, if you like, we can write
this in symbols. That basically, Li is
Li等于R_i-1，然后Ri更复杂
simply equal to R_i-1. And Ri,
let's see, that's the more complicated
Ri等于。。我们跟着这条线
Ri等于Fi应用到
one. Ri is equal, well, let's just follow
the lines here. Ri is just equal to Fi
R_i-1，再异或Li，对吧？
applied to, R_i-1 XOR Li. Okay?
So this, and this is basically, i goes
这里i从1到d。这个方程定义了一个Feistel网络
from, 1 to d. So this is the, equation
that defines a Feistel network, mapping a
将一个2n位输入映射到2n位输出
所以我们这里有
2n bit input to 2n bit outputs. So
here we have the, again, I just copied the
我刚刚复制了Feistel网络的图
令人惊讶的论断是，事实上
picture of the Feistel network. And the
amazing claim is that, in fact, it doesn't
与你给我的函数们F1到Fd无关
对于这些给我的函数
matter which functions you give me. For
any functions, F1 to FD that you give me,
构造出的Feistel网络事实上是可逆的
the resulting Feistel network function is,
in fact, invertible. And the way we're
我们证明的方法是构造出它的一个逆
going to prove that is basically we're
going to construct an inverse, because not
因为它不仅可逆，而且它的逆可被有效计算。
那么我们来看看
only is it invertible, it's efficiently
invertible. So let's see. So let's look at
我们先看一回合Feistel网络：
这里是输入Ri和Li
one round of a Feistel network, so
here, this is the inputs, Ri, Li, and this
这是输出R_i+1和L_i+1。现在我问大家
如何求这个的逆呢？
is the output R_i+1, L_i+1. And now what I'm
going to ask you is to invert this.
那我们看看。假设我们有的输入是R_i+1和L_i+1
So let's see. So suppose now the input that
we're given is R_i+1, L_i+1 and we want to
我们想计算Ri和Li。我们想计算这一回合
从相反的方向来
compute Ri, Li. So we want to compute the
round in the reverse direction. So let's
我们看看行不行。好，我们先看Ri。
Ri非常简单
see if we can do it. Well, let's look at
Ri. So, Ri is very easy. Basically, Ri is
Ri就等于L_i+1。所有L_i+1就成为了R_i
现在我问大家
just equal to L_i+1. So L_i+1 just becomes
R_i. But now, let me ask you, to write the
写出L_i的表达式，用R_i+1和L_i+1表示
expression for L_i in terms of R_i+1, and L_i+1.
那么我希望大家都写出来了，
将L_i+1输入到函数F_i+1
So I hope everybody sees that, basically, L_i+1
is fed into the function F_i+1.
函数结果跟R_i+1异或，答案就是L_i
The result is XORed with R_i+1,
and that gives the L_i input.
这就是Feistel网络一轮的逆
So this the inverse of one round
of a Feistel network.
如果我们画成这幅图，写下逆的构造图
And if we draw this as a diagram, let's just
write the picture for the inverse.
大家注意输入是R_i+1, L_i+1
输出是Ri和Li，对吧？
So here you notice the input is R_i+1, L_i+1
and the output is Ri, Li. Right?
我们在计算每回合的逆
大家注意到Feistel回合的逆
So we're computing, we're inverting, the
rounds. So you notice that the inverse of
和正向Feistel网络本身长得很像
a Feistel round looks pretty much the
same as the Feistel round in the
由于技术原因，字面上看
forward direction. It's literally, you
know, just for a technical reason, it's
它们互为镜像，构造是相同的
kinda the mirror image of one another. But
it's basically, the same construct. And
当我们一起用这些回合的逆时
when we put these inverted rounds back
together. We essentially get the inverse
我们就可以获得整个Feistel网络的逆了。
那么大家注意到我们从第D个回合开始
of the entire Feistel network. So you
notice we start off with the round number D
计算第D个回合的逆，然后计算
第D-1个回合的逆，等等
with the inverse of round number D,
then we do the inverse of round number D-1
直到我们获得了第一回合的逆
and so on and so forth until we
get to the inverse of the first round. And
我们得到了最后的输出R0和L0
这就是输入
we get our final outputs which is R0, L0,
like this is the inputs and we manage to
这样我们设法用Rd和Ld，计算出R0和L0。有趣的是
invert basically Rd, Ld and get R0, L0
and the interesting thing is that
这些求逆的计算和加密的计算非常类似
basically these inversion circuits look
pretty much the same as the encryption
唯一的不同是函数应用的顺序正好相反
circuits and the only difference is that
the functions are applied in reverse order.
我们从Fd出发，到F1结束。当我们加密时
Right we started with Fd and ended with
F1. Whereas when we were encrypting, we
从F1出发，到Fd结束。所以，对硬件设计者而言
started with F1 and ended with Fd. So, for
hardware designers, this is very
这个非常吸引人，因为想节省硬件开销
attractive, because, basically, if you
wanna save hardware, you realize that your
加密硬件要和解密硬件一样
encryption hardware is identical to your
decryption hardware. So you only have to
所以大家只需要实现一个算法即可
同时可以获得两个算法
implement one algorithm, and you get both
algorithms the same way. The only
唯一的不同在于函数应用的顺序相反
difference is that the functions are
applied in reverse order. Okay. So this
好的，这个Feistel机制是个构造可逆函数的一般方法
Feistel mechanism is a general method
for building invertible functions from
根据任意函数F1到Fd。事实上
它在很多不同的分组密码中都有应用
arbitrary functions F1 to Fd and in fact,
it's used in many different block ciphers.
不过有趣的是，AES没有使用它
Although, interestingly, it's not actually
used in AES. So, there are many other
有许多其他分组密码用了Feistel网络
当然，它们的回合函数
block ciphers that use a Feistel
network. Or, of course, they differ from
与DES中的F1到Fd不同。但是AES
使用了一个完全不同的结构类型
DES in the functions F1 to Fd. But AES
actually uses a completely different type
并非Feistel网络，过几节
of structure that's actually not a
Feistel network. We'll see how AES
我们会看到AES的工作原理。
现在我们知道了Feistel网络是什么了
works in a couple of segments. So now that
we know what Feistel networks are, let
让我提一个关于Feistel网络的重要定理
me mention an important theorem about the
theory of Feistel networks that shows
用来证实Feistel网络是个好办法
这个定理由Luby和Rackoff于1985年提出
why they're a good idea. This theorem is
due to Luby and Rackoff back in 1985, and it
表述如下。假设我有一个安全的伪随机函数
says the following. Suppose I have a
function that is a secure pseudorandom
(参见论文How to construct pseudorandom
permutations from pseudorandom functions)
那么它与定义在N位字符串上的随机函数不可区分
function, okay. So it's indistinguishable
from random and happens to act on N bits.
所以它使用密钥K将N位字符串映射到N位字符串
So it maps N bits to N bits and uses a
key K. Then, it turns out, that if you use
如果在三轮Feistel网络中使用这个函数
最后得到的是一个安全的伪随机置换
this function in three rounds of a Feistel
network. What you end up with is a secure
换句话说，最终得到的是一个可逆函数
pseudo random permutation. In other words,
what you end up with is an invertible
它与真随机函数不可区分
function that is indistinguishable from a
truly random invertible function. And I
我希望大家还记得安全的分组密码的定义
hope you remember that the true definition
of a secure block cipher is that it needs
它需要一个安全的伪随机置换。这个定理说
to be a secure pseudo random permutation.
So what this theorem says, is that if you
如果你从一个安全的伪随机函数出发
最后可以得到一个安全的分组密码
start with a secure pseudo random
function, you end up with a secure block
就是这些。让我再解释得更多一点
cipher. Basically, that's what this is.
And let me explain in a little bit more
到底发生什么了。本质上
PRF在Feistel网络的每一回合里
detail what's actually going on here. So,
essentially, the PRF is used in every
都被使用。换句话说
round of the Feistel network. So, in
other words, here, what's actually
PRF使用密钥K0计算
computed is the PRF using one secret key,
K0. Here, what's computed is the PRF
当然，使用另一不同密钥对付R1
using a different secret key, of course
applied to R1. And here we have yet
这里我们还有另一密钥K1，对付R1；K2对付R2。大家注意
another secret key, K1 applied, K2 applied
to R2. And you notice, this is why,
这就是为什么Feistel机制使用K^3里的密钥
basically this Feistel construction,
uses keys in K cubed. In other words, it
换句话说，它使用了三个独立的密钥
密钥独立这点很重要
uses three independent keys. So it's very
important that the keys are actually
所以我们需要三个独立的密钥
independent. So really, we need three,
independent keys. And then we end up with
然后我们最后得到了一个安全的伪随机置换
好，那就是支撑Feistel网络的理论
a secure pseudorandom permutation. Okay,
so that's the theory behind Feistel
现在我们理解了，可以看看DES的特例了
networks. And now that we understand that,
we can actually look at the specifics of DES.
DES有16回合的Feistel网络，好的
So DES is basically a sixteen round
Feistel network, okay. So there are
有函数F1到F16，将32位字符串映射到
32位字符串，因此
functions F1 to F16 that map 32 bits to
32 bits, and as a result, the DES itself
DES本身是作用于64位分组上的，2x32
现在DES里的16个回合函数
acts on 64 bit blocks, 2x32. Now the
sixteen round functions in DES are
都是由一个函数F推导而来的
只不过回合密钥不同
actually all derived from a single
function F. Just used with different keys.
事实上，每轮的回合密钥不同。Ki是回合密钥
So in fact, these are the different round
keys. So Ki is, a round key. And it's
由DES的56位主密钥推导而来
basically derived from the key K, derived
from the 56 bit DES key K. Okay and I'll
我待会再来描述这个函数F
describe what this function F is in just a
minute. But basically that, you see that
大家看到有16个不同的回合密钥
我们得到了16个不同的回合函数
by using sixteen different round keys, we
get sixteen different round functions. And
这给我们Feistel网络。所以从高层看DES的工作
that gives us the Feistel network. So just
on a high level how the DES works
你有64位输入。第一件事是
basically you have a 64 bit input. The
first thing it does is, this initial
初始置换仅是置换这64位字符串
它把第0位换到第6位
permutation that just permutes the 64 bits
around. Namely it maps bit number one to
把第2位换到第17位，等等
bit number six. Bit number two to bit
number seventeen, and so on. This is not
这并不是出于安全考虑，仅仅是标准里的要求
for security reasons, this is just
specified in the standard. Then we go into
然后进行16轮Feistel网络
现在大家知道它怎么工作的了
the sixteen round Feistel network. That
actually, you now know how it works.
使用函数F1到F16，如前所述
Basically uses the function F1 to F16, as
specified before. And then, basically we
我们还有另一个置换，叫最终置换
have another permutation, it's called the
final permutation. That's just the inverse
就是初始置换的逆置换，还是置换各位
of the initial permutation. Again,
it just permutes bits around, this is not
并非出于安全考量。然后我们得到的就是最终输出了
necessary for security reasons. And then
we finally get, the final outputs. Okay.
好，现在，如前所述，有一步密钥扩张
我这里不细讲它
Now, as we said, there's a key expansion
step, which I'm not gonna describe. But
这里56位DES密钥被扩张成了这些回合密钥
basically, this 56-bit DES key is expanded
into these rounds keys. Where each round
每一轮密钥48位。这样我们有了16个48位回合密钥
key, is 48 bits. Okay, so we have sixteen
48 bit round keys, and they're basically
分别用在DES的16个回合里
当你想将这个密码倒过来的时候
used in the sixteen rounds of DES. And
then when you want to invert the cipher,
你只需要使用这些回合密钥
all you do is you use these, round keys,
these sixteen round keys, in reverse
以相反的顺序。好的，现在我们理解了DES结构
唯一剩下的
order. Okay, so now that we understand the
DES structure, the only thing that's left
就是指定函数F了。让我来解释一下
to do is specify the function, capital F.
So let me explain how this function works.
它取32位字符串X作为输入
So basically, it takes, as inputs, its, 32
bit value, let's call it X. But in
实际上这是R0,R1,R2,R3等等
reality, you remember, this is R0,
R1, R2, R3, so on and so
有32位。然后它还取48位回合密钥为输入
forth. These are 32 bit values. And then
it takes, also, a 48 bit round key. So
所有我们这里有密钥Ki，48位
here we have our key Ki, which happens to
be 48 bits. The first thing it does, is it
第一件事，通过一个扩张盒子
这个扩张盒子取32位输入
goes through an expansion box. And this
expansion box basically take thirty two
映射到48位字符串。所有的扩张盒子
bits, and maps them into 48 bits. Now, all
the expansion box does is just replicates
只是复制某些位，移动其他位
例如，X的第1位
some bits, and move other bits around. So,
for example, bit #1 of X is replicated
被复制到了输出的位置2；
X的第2位被放到了输出的第3位
into positions 2 and 48 in the output.
Bit #2 of X is positioned in as bit
等等。仅仅是复制X的一些位
#3 of the output. And so on and so
forth, just by replicating some of the
我们将其扩张成了48位。下一件事是
bits of X, we expand the input into 48
bits. The next thing we do is we compute
我们计算扩张结果和回合密钥的异或
有时人们说密码学家们
an XOR with the round key.
Sometimes people say that cryptographers
只会计算异或，这就是个例子
我们在这个函数里只计算异或
only compute XORs. This is an example of
that, where, well, we just do XORs in this
然后DES里的魔法部分来了！这48位字符串
function. And then comes the magic of DES,
where, actually, these 48 bits are broken
被分解成8组，每组6位。6，7，8。。让我画
into eight groups of six bits. Six, seven,
eight. And so let me draw, and then what
然后。。哦对，这里每一个都是6位
happens is, so yes. Each one of these,
each one of these wires is, six bits. And
然后它们进入了S盒子
then they, they go into what, what are
called S boxes. And I'll explain S boxes
我稍后解释S盒子。这些S盒子是DES的智慧所在
in just a minute. The S boxes are kind of
the smarts of, DES. And then, the S
S盒子是一个映射，6位到4位
所以S盒子的输出是这些4位字符串
box is basically a map, six bits to four
bits. So, the outputs of the S boxes are
它们被收集起来，形成了32位，对吧？
these four bits. They're collected. This
gives up 32 bits, right? Eight groups of
8组4位，给我们32位字符串
最后应用另一置换
four bits, gives us 32 bits and then
finally this is fed into yet another
移动各个位，比如
permutation which just maps the bits
around. So, for example bit number one
第1位移至第9位，第2位移至第15位，等等
will go to bit number nine, bit number two
will go to bit number fifteen and so on.
它只置换32个位，最终得到函数F的输出32位
So it just permutes the 32 bits around and
that's the final 32 bit output of this F function.
对吧？通过使用不同的回合密钥
Okay? So by using different
round keys, essentially, we get different
我们获得了不同的回合函数
那就是我们如何构造DES的16个回合函数的过程
round functions, and that's how we form
the sixteen round functions of DES. Now,
现在，唯一剩下没讲的是这些S盒子
the only thing that, left to specify are
these S boxes. So the S boxes, literally,
这些S盒子是6位映射到4位的函数
它们使用了一个查找表来实现
are just functions from six bits to four
bits. They are just implemented as a look
描述一个6位到4位的函数
up table. Right? So describing a function
from six bits to four bits basically
只要写出所有2的六次方个可能输入
所对应的输出即可
amounts to writing the output of the
function on all two to the six possible inputs.
2的六次方是64.所有我们只需一张表，包含64个值
Two to the six is 64. So we just
have a table that literally contains 64 values.
每个值是4位字符串。那么这是个例子
Where each value is four bits. So
here is an example, this happens to be the
在第5个S盒子里，这是一张表包含64个值
fifth S box, and you see that this is a
table that contains 64 values right?
4行16列，共64个值。例如，如果你想查找输出
It's four by sixteen. So, 64 values. For
example, if you wanna look at, the output,
对应于011011的输出。好，那么你看这两位，01
that corresponds to 0-1-1-0-1-1. Okay, then
you look at these two bits. This is 01,
然后看这四位1101，然后就能查到对应输出是1001
and these four bits are 1101, and you see
that the output is 1001. The four bits
四位输出1001。所有S盒子是用这些表实现的
output 1001. Okay, so the S boxes are just
implemented as these tables.
现在问题是，这些S盒子是如何选取的呢？
设计者为什么要这样设计它们呢？
Now the question is, how are these S boxes chosen.
How are these tables actually chosen by
那么为了给大家直观理解
the designers of this. So to give you some
intuitions for that, lets start with a
我们从一个非常糟糕的S盒子开始
假设这些S盒子是线性的
very bad choice for S boxes. So imagine
the S boxes were linear. What do I mean by
什么意思？设想这些S盒子仅仅是将6位输入
that? I mean that imagine that these six
bit inputs literally were just
以不同的方式进行异或，然后输出4位
XORed with one another in different
ways to produce the four bit outputs.
好，另一种表示方法是
我们可以把S盒子写成矩阵向量积的形式
Okay, another way of writing that is that
we can write the S box as a matrix vector product.
那么这里有矩阵Ai，有6位的向量X
So here you have the matrix Ai.
And the vector, the six bit vector X.
大家看到，如果我写成矩阵向量积
And you can see that, if we write this matrix
vector product, basically, we take the
那么我们取这个向量和这个输入向量的内积
记住，它们都是0,1字符串
inner product of this vector with the
input vector. Remember, these are all bits.
是6位的向量内积。另一个6位向量
So the six bits vector inner
product. Another six bit vector, and we do
我们取模2，大家看到，我们在计算X2异或X3
that modulo two, you realize, basically,
what we're computing is X2 XOR X3.
对吧？因为只有第2位和第3位才有1
Right? Because only position two and
position three have 1's in it.
类似地，下一个内积会产生X1异或X4异或X5
And similarly the next, inner product will
produce X1 XOR X4 XOR X5 and so on and
等等。好的，所有大家可以看到
如果S盒子是用这种方式实现的
so forth. Okay. So you can literally see
that if the S boxes are implemented this
所做的仅仅是将矩阵A应用到向量X上
way. Then, all they do, is just apply the
matrix A to the input vector X. Which is
所以我们说，这时S盒子是完全线性的
why we say, that in this case the S boxes
are completely linear. Now, I claimed that
我说，如果S盒子是线性的，DES将一点都不安全的
in fact that if the S boxes were linear, then DES
would be totally insecure. The reason is,
原因是，如果S盒子是线性的，那么DES所做的
if the S boxes are linear, then all that
DES does is just compute XOR of various
无非是计算异或、置换各位而已
只有异或和位的置换
things and permute and shuffle bits
around. So it's just XORs and bit
因此所有DES都只是一个线性函数
permutations, which means that as a
result, all of DES is just a linear
换句话说，存在一个矩阵B，以这些为维数
function. In other words, there will be a
Matrix B. Of these dimensions. Basically,
如果矩阵B有宽度832
it's a matrix B that has width 832.
Basically what I will do is I will write
(832=64+48*16)
我只需要写下64位明文分组和16个回合密钥
形成一个很长的向量
the 64 bit message plus the sixteen round
keys as one long vector. Alright, so the
明文64位，有16个回合密钥，每个48位
message is 64 bits and there are sixteen
round keys. Each one is 48 and that, if
加起来就是832，对吧？我写下这些值、密钥
you do the math, it's basically 832. Okay?
So I write these values, the keys and the
和明文分组，形成一个长向量，然后有这个矩阵
message, as one long vector and then there
will be this matrix that essentially when
当你计算这些矩阵向量积时
你可以得到密文的各个位的值
you compute these matrix vector products.
Essentially you get the different bits of
所以矩阵有64行，因为密文分组有64位
the ciphertext. So there's 64 of these
rows and as a result, you get 64 bits of
好，这就是线性DES的意思
ciphertext. Okay, so this is what it
means for DES to be linear. So if you
大家稍微想一想，就会发现S盒子是DES中
think a little bit about this, you realize
that the S boxes are the only nonlinear
唯一非线性的结构。如果S盒子是线性的
那么整个DES算法就是线性的
part of DES. So if the S boxes were
linear, then the entire circuit is linear
所以就可以使用矩阵来表示了
如果是线性的这种情况的话
and therefore can be expressed as this
matrix. Now if that's the case then DES
DES就是一个糟糕的伪随机置换了
would be terrible as a secure pseudorandom
permutation. And let me give you a very
我给大家一个非常简单的例子
如果你计算3个DES的输出的异或
simple example. Basically if you did the
XOR of three outputs of DES, well
想想这意味着什么？看定义了DES的矩阵B
let's think what that means. Basically we
would be looking at B times, the matrix B
B乘以一个向量，再异或B乘以另一个向量
that defines DES, times, one vector
XOR B times another vector,
异或B乘以第三个向量。我们可以提取矩阵B
XOR B times a third vector. We
could take the B out of the parentheses so
就变成了B乘以这个向量
当然了，K异或K异或K
we'd be basically doing B times this
vector over here. But of course K XOR K XOR K,
还是K。所有想想这意味着什么？
this is just K. And so if you
think about what that means, basically we
我们获得了取密钥为K，DES在点
M1异或M2异或M3处的加密结果
just got back DES of K at the point
M1 XOR M2 XOR M3. But this means that now DES
这意味着现在DES有这么糟糕的关系
这是可以被测试的，对吧？
has this horrible relation. That can be
tested. Right? So, basically, if you
那么，如果你将这三个明文M1, M2, M3
的输出结果异或
XOR the output of three values,
M1, M2, M3, you'll get the value of
就可以得到在点M1异或M2异或M3处的
DES加密结果。这不是一个随机函数
DES, at the point M1 XOR M2 XOR M3. Now this
is not a relation that is going to hold
应该有的关系。一个随机函数无法满足这个等式
for a random function. A random function
is not going to satisfy this equality.
(或者说，以极小概率成立)
那么大家有了一个非常简单的测试
可以告诉我们DES不是随机函数
And so you get a very easy test to tell you
that DES is not a random function.
事实上，也许可以留给大家作为练习。不难看出
In fact, maybe you can take that as a small
exercise. It's not even difficult to see,
给定足够的输入、输出对，是可以
还原出整个密钥的
that given enough input output pairs, you
can literally recover the entire secret key.
是的，你需要832个输入、输出对
就可以还原出整个密钥
Yeah. You just need 832 input output
pairs, and you'll be able recover the
如果S盒子是线性的，DES将一点都不安全
entire secret key. And so if the S boxes
were linear, DES would be completely
实际上，即使S盒子和线性相近
insecure. It turns out, actually, even if
the S boxes were close to being linear. In
换句话说，大多数时候S盒子的表现是线性的
比如64次中有60次是线性的
other words, the S boxes were linear most
of the time. So maybe for 60 out of the 64
这实际上也足够破解DES了
inputs, the S boxes were linear. It turns
out that would also be enough to break
我们稍后就会看到为什么
特别的，如果你随机地选择S盒子里的值
DES, and we're gonna see why later on. In
particular, if you choose the S boxes at
实际上结果还是有些接近于线性函数
random, it turns out they'll tend to be
somewhat close to linear functions. As a
我们还是可以破解DES，还原密钥
result, you'll be able to totally break
DES. You'll just be able to recover the
用非常少的时间。因此，DES的设计者们
key, in basically, very little time. And
so, the designers of DES actually
给出了一些他们选择S盒子时的规则
specified a number of rules they use for
choosing the S boxes. And it's not
不奇怪，第一条就是这些函数要与
线性函数差很远才行
surprising, the first rule is that these
functions are far away from being linear.
好，换句话说，没有线性函数以较大比例
Okay. So, in other words, there is no
function that agrees with a large fraction
能和S盒子的输出吻合。还有这些其他规则
of the outputs of the S box. And then
there are all these other rules, for
例如，都是4个到1个的映射，对吧？
example, there are exactly four to one
maps, right? So, every output has exactly
每个输出都有4个原像，等等。所以
我们理解了为什么要这样选择S盒子
four pre-images and so on and so forth. So
we understand now why they chose the S
事实上，这些S盒子可以抵抗特定的攻击
boxes they way they did and in fact its
all done to defeat certain attacks on DES.
好，这就是DES的描述
Okay. So that's the end of the
description of DES, and in the next few
下面几节我们看DES的安全性
segments we are going to look at the
security of DES.